<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="jaluino_userguide">
  <title>Description</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>Sébastien Lelong</author>
    <author>Richard Zengerink</author>
    <publisher>Jaluino Group</publisher>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <section>
      <title>Overview</title>
      <p>TODO: picture overview</p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Board and shield sizes</title>
      <p>Jaluino Medium board size is rather bigger than Arduino Duemilanove board. This is mainly because microntroller itself is bigger (it has more pins). Jaluino board is also single side, to be easier to build at home. Finally, Jaluino provides more features, like a serial connector<fn>Arduino only provides USB, or serial on older versions, but not both</fn> and an I²C connector.</p>
      <p><fig>
          <title>Jaluino Medium under construction, compared to Arduino Duemilanove.</title>
          <image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_medium_arduino_comparison.jpg" width="300" placement="break"/>
        </fig></p>
      <p>Jaluino shield aera is smaller than the board itself, whereas Arduino&apos;s shield have quite the same size as the board.</p>
      <p>Here are Jaluino board and shield sizes specifications:</p>
      <p><table frame="all">
          <title>Board size specifications</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Length</entry>
                <entry>4.6&quot; (or 11.8cm)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Width</entry>
                <entry>3.4&quot; (or 8.6cm)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table><table frame="all">
          <title>Shield size specifications</title>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1"/>
            <colspec colname="c2"/>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>Length</entry>
                <entry>3.4&quot; (or 8.6cm)</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>Width</entry>
                <entry>3.1&quot; (or 8cm)</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table></p>
      <p><fig>
          <title>Jauino Medium with Crumboard shield plugged, showing board and shield size differences</title>
          <image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_medium_crumboard_plugged.jpg" width="300" placement="break"/>
        </fig></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Exposed pins through shield connectors</title>
      <p>The following diagram shows 18F4550 pin layout, beside Jaluino shield connector. This is an important diagram, as it shows relation between PIC&apos;s pins and connectors, which pins is exposed<fn>&quot;Exposed&quot; means pin available on shields.</fn>, which is not.</p>
      <p><fig>
          <title>Jaluino Medium pin layout mapping related to shield connectors</title>
          <image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_medium_pin_layout.png" width="500" placement="break" otherprops="clickable"/>
        </fig></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Power and voltages specifications</title>
      <p>Jaluino medium comes with three power sources, and two voltages available on-board. Power sources can be either:<ul>
          <li><b>AC/DC adaptor</b>, usually delivering up to 12V. Input voltage must be at least 9V. This kind of adaptor can deliver lots of power (typical cheap ones deliver something like 1A).</li>
          <li><b>USB</b>, power is directly taken from USB connector. USB outputs 5V and usually can deliver up to 500mA.</li>
          <li><b>serial module</b>, where such modules can also provide power (like a USB-to-serial module). Serial module needs to outputs 5V.</li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>Depending on how much power you need, you may use one these options.</p>
      <p>Jaluino Medium provides two voltages available on-board, 5V and 3.3V:<ul>
          <li><b>5V</b> : when using AC/DC adaptor, input voltage is regulated by 7805. This component outputs regulated 5V, which is a typical voltage used to power a microcontroller such a PIC 18F4550. When using USB or serial as power sources, no 5V regulation is done: this means there should be 5V as output (USB outputs 5V, if you use your serial module to power the board, make sure it outpus 5V).</li>
          <li><b>3.3V</b> : whatever the power sources, another voltage regulator produces 3.3V from 5V. Jaluino Medium makes your life easier and provides this commonly used voltage, which is sometime used by specific components. </li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Jaluino Medium version <i>a</i> and version <i>b</i></title>
      <p>3.3V voltage regulator is kind of a special component: there are different regulators, not that easily available, quite expensive and not using the same pin layout. That&apos;s why Jaluino Medium comes in two flavors, depending on the pin layout<fn>Having two versions actually adds complexity to maintenance and designs. We, at Jaluino Group, wanted to provide both options at the beginning, until we can make a final decision... Which one would you prefer ?</fn>:<ul>
          <li>
            <p><b>Version a</b>: this version uses pin layout <i>Ground/Output/Input</i>. </p>
            <fig>
              <title>3.3V regulator pin layout for version <i>a</i><image placement="break" href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_va_layout.png"/></title>
            </fig>
            <p>The following components use this pin layout, and can be used to build <b>Jaluino Medium version a</b>: LD1117V33, LM1117T, LM1086.</p>
          </li>
          <li>
            <p><b>Version b</b>: this version uses pin layout <i>Input/Ground/Ouput</i>.</p>
            <fig>
              <title>3.3V regulator pin layout for version <i>b</i></title>
              <image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_vb_layout.png"/>
            </fig>
            <p>The following components use this pin layout, and can be used to build <b>Jaluino Medium version b</b>: LM3940, LF33V.</p>
          </li>
        </ul></p>
      <p>Choosing version <i>a</i> or version <i>b</i> really is just about selecting which regulator you mostly can find, at lowest price. Jaluino features remain the same.</p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
