<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- This document was created with Syntext Serna Free. --><!DOCTYPE topic PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DITA Topic//EN" "topic.dtd" []>
<topic id="jaluino_schematics">
  <title>Hardware setup</title>
  <prolog>
    <author>Sébastien Lelong</author>
    <author>Richard Zengerink</author>
    <publisher>Jaluino Group</publisher>
  </prolog>
  <body>
    <p>As previously described (see <xref href="jaluino_medium_description.xml#jaluino_medium_description/overview">here</xref>), <b>Jaluino Medium</b> can be configured on board, with several jumpers. This section describes how to setup these jumpers, showing the different combinations.</p>
    <section>
      <title>Power sources selection</title>
      <p>Jaluino can be powered using different sources (see <xref href="jaluino_medium_description.xml#jaluino_medium_description/powersources">here</xref> for power specifications): a classical AC/DC adaptor, using USB connector or through a serial module (typically a USB-to-serial adaptor). These different possibilities can be configured with jumpers <b>JP1</b>, <b>JP2</b>, <b>JP3</b> and <b>JP4</b>.</p>
      <p>JP1, JP2 and JP3 Jumpers are located on top left and JP4 is located on top right, near serial connector.</p>
      <p><fig>
          <title>Four jumpers allow to setup power sources<image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_medium_power_jumpers.jpg" width="500" placement="break"/></title>
        </fig></p>
      <p>Valid combinations are the following:<ul>
          <li>One jumper can be plugged on JP1, JP2 <b>or</b> JP3.<ul>
              <li><b>JP1</b>: power source comes from AC/DC adaptor, plugged on <b>jack</b></li>
              <li><b>JP2</b>: power source comes from <b>USB</b> connector</li>
              <li>JP3: power source comes from <b>serial module</b></li>
            </ul></li>
          <li>If power source comes jack or USB (JP1 or JP2), power can be used to power the serial module itself, by plugging a jumper on <b>JP4</b> (&quot;<i>source serial</i>&quot;). It doesn&apos;t make any sense to put a jumper on JP3 and JP4.</li>
        </ul><note type="caution">putting a jumper on JP3 and another JP4 is an <b>invalid combination</b>. Don&apos;t do this, as <b>your Jaluino board won&apos;t be protected by fuse anymore</b> !</note></p>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Serial setup</title>
      <p>Two jumpers can be used to setup serial, basically to configure RTS and CTS. Involved jumpers are <b>JP7</b> and <b>J7</b>, they are located on top right of the board, near serial connector. </p>
      <p><fig>
          <title>Two jumpers are involved in serial setup (RTS and CTS)</title>
          <image href="../../images/mainboard/jaluino_medium_serial_jumpers.jpg" width="500" placement="break"/>
        </fig></p>
      <p><ul>
          <li><b>JP7</b>: if enabled (jumper plugged), then CTS line is connected to pin <i>RD5</i>. This feature is usually not needed for basic serial communications, but if you need to deal with CTS logic (hardware flow control), you can enable this and handle CTS line using this pin.</li>
          <li><b>J7</b>: this jumper is a tri-state trigger. You can plug a jumper on 1-2 segment, 2-3 segment, or not jumper at all.<ul>
              <li><b>1-2 segment</b>: a jumper is plugged, covering the two left pins. In this configuration, <b>Reset-via-RTS</b> is active. This means acting on RTS, for example from a PC, will actually perform reset (PIC is restarting). This feature is mostly important when using a bootloader, and if you want to upload and control your board without having to manually push the Reset button.</li>
              <li><b>2-3 segment</b>: in this configuration, RTS line gets connected to pin <i>RD4</i>. As enabling CTS line, this configuration is rarely used in most serial communication, but might be useful if you need to perform some hardware flow control.</li>
              <li><b>no jumper</b>: this configuration disables any of the two configurations above. Neither Reset-via-RTS nor RTS line are enabled.</li>
            </ul><p><fig>
                <title>Setting up RTS jumper</title>
                <image href="../../images/mainboard/rts_reset.png" placement="break"/>
                <p><i>Enabling Reset-via-RTS</i></p>
                <image href="../../images/mainboard/rts_line.png" placement="break"/>
                <p><i>Enabling RTS line</i></p>
                <image href="../../images/mainboard/rts_clear.png" placement="break"/>
                <p><i>No RTS setup</i></p>
              </fig></p></li>
        </ul></p>
    </section>
  </body>
</topic>
